{"tossups": [{"question": "This organization deployed the ISAF shortly after the only time it has ever invoked Article 5. In March 2017, opposition leaders in Montenegro wrote to Steve Bannon to ask him to block Montenegro\u2019s accession to this organization. Donald Trump has repeatedly complained that members of this organization are not spending 2 percent of their GDP on defense. For ten points, name this military alliance which consists of the United States, Canada and various European countries.", "answer": "<b> N</b>orth<b> A</b>tlantic<b> T</b>reaty<b> O</b>rganization", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Over 100 civilians died during Operation Carthage in one of these buildings in Copenhagen when it was struck by RAF bombers as collateral. One of these institutions served as the headquarters for the White Rose anti-Nazi movement in Munich, and another of these institutions was transformed into the S-21 prison camp by the Khmer Rouge. A sacred olive grove dedicated to Athena surrounded an ancient example of one of these institutions founded by Plato. For ten points, name these institutions that include the Lyceum and Plato\u2019s Academy.", "answer": "<b> school</b>s (accept<b> boarding school</b>s,<b> universities</b>, etc.)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This composer wrote a<em> Missa Solemnis</em> mass for Archduke Randolph, his patron. He commemorated the Battle of Vitoria with the piece<em> Wellington\u2019s Victory</em> and donated its funds to victims of the Peninsular War. This composer allegedly dedicated a piece to Napoleon until the decision to establish an empire prompted this man to rip that piece in half and dedicate it to \u201cthe memory of a great man.\u201d For ten points, name this composer of the<em> Emperor</em> piano concerto and the<em> Eroica</em> symphony.", "answer": "Ludwig van<b> Beethoven</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Though this general was pushed back to Gazala during Operation Crusader, he managed to capture Tobruk from Claude Auchinleck shortly after. This man\u2019s strategy of setting wooden poles to block glider landings led the logs to become known as this man\u2019s \u201casparagus.\u201d This man was put in charge of defending the Atlantic Wall during D-Day two years after he lost to Bernard Montgomery at the First Battle of El Alamein. For ten points, name this German general whose North African campaigns earned him the nickname \u201cDesert Fox.\u201d", "answer": "Erwin<b> Rommel</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The sociologist Phil Zuckerman primarily studies societies where this belief is prevalent. John Lennox debated a writer holding this philosophical position in 2008. Baron d\u2019Holbach\u2019s 18th-century book<em> The</em> <em>System of Nature</em> was widely criticized for holding this belief. Another advocate for this philosophical position argued against its alternative in 1986\u2019s<em> The Blind Watchmaker</em>. Christopher Hitchens and Richard Dawkins are among the \u201cFour Horsemen\u201d of, for ten points, what philosophical stance that rejects the existence of God?", "answer": "<b> atheism</b> (accept descriptions of<b> believing there is no God</b>; do not accept or prompt on agnosticism or descriptions of \u201cquestioning whether there is a God\u201d)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This location was the subject of a 2007 controversy when John Fire Lame Deer symbolically planted a prayer staff into the ground. Doane Robinson initially intended for Lewis and Clark to be honored at this site. To work on this project, its sculptor abandoned a relief honoring Jefferson Davis and Stonewall Jackson at Stone Mountain. Gutzon Borglum designed, for ten points, what South Dakota landmark that features the faces of Washington, Lincoln, Roosevelt, and Jefferson?", "answer": "<b> Mount Rushmore</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This figure met an illegitimate Byzantine princess named Bayalan while visiting an Uzbek ruler. This figure was employed as a judge by both the ruler of the Maldives and the Sultan of Delhi. This man criticized the women of Mali for not covering themselves and documented his expedition to China in his <em>Travels</em>, which began after his first pilgrimage to Mecca. For ten points, name this Moroccan traveler that crossed much of the medieval Islamic world.", "answer": "Abu Abdallah Muhammad<b> Ibn Battuta</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Different ways to do this activity are listed in a \u201cRag\u201d written by Phil Ochs. David Harris founded an organization that advocated for this action and was symbolized by the letter omega, for ohm. Common methods of doing this included wearing women\u2019s underwear to feign homosexuality, one of a number of ways to get 4-F status. One of Jimmy Carter\u2019s first acts as president was pardoning people who had performed, for ten points, what action by which people avoided fighting in the Vietnam War?", "answer": "<b> draft dodging</b> the Vietnam War (accept synonyms for dodge, including<b> draft evasion</b> and <b>draft avoidance</b>; accept equivalents such as<b> avoiding military</b> service in Vietnam; prompt on resisting the draft and/or protesting the Vietnam War)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During a power struggle, this man stabbed his former ally, John Comyn, at a monastery in Dumfries. This man\u2019s claim to the throne was defended in a letter to Pope John XXII in the Declaration of Arbroath. This man\u2019s Treaty of Corbeil renewed the Auld Alliance with France, and he assumed the position of Guardian after the defeat at Falkirk of William Wallace. For ten points, name this Scottish king who was defeated the English at the Battle of Bannockburn.", "answer": "<b> Robert the Bruce</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A tunnel built in this city connected Dobrinja [doh-brin-ya] and Butmir, allowing civilian escape and the inflow of humanitarian aid. The Markale [mar-kah-lay] massacres occurred in this city, where a battle was triggered by protests in front of a Holiday Inn. Stanislav Gali\u00b4c [gall-itch] was convicted of crimes against humanity for his actions in this city. The attacking forces of the Republika Srpska replaced those of the Yugoslav People\u2019s Army in this city, where fighting was ended by the Dayton Accords. For ten points, name this capital city that was brutally besieged during the Bosnian War.", "answer": "Siege of<b> Sarajevo</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name the first prime minister of Israel.", "answer": "David<b> Ben-Gurion</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This essay quotes from a burial song for Marines to show that a straw man has no more worth than an animal. This essay argues against a similar chapter by William Paley by claiming that expediency is not a sufficient excuse to abstain from revolution. This work wonders what form of government could follow after monarchy and democracy, noting that its author \u201cheartily accepts the motto \u2018that government is best which governs least\u2019,\u201d and repeatedly voices opposition to the Mexican War and to slavery. For ten points, name this 1849 essay promoting non-violent protesting by Henry David Thoreau.", "answer": "<b> Civil Disobedience</b> (or<b> Resistance to Civil Government</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In Roman tradition, these people were the dedicatees of poems called<em> epithalamium</em> and wore a yellow article of clothing called a<em> flammeum</em>. According to a popular theory, Rembrandt painted one of these people being given a necklace and being embraced by a man representing Isaac; that painting is known as \u201cThe Jewish [one of these people].\u201d According to some interpretations, a figure in a green dress is one of these people in a painting by Jan van Eyck that also shows the merchant Giovanni Arnolfini. For ten points, name these women who often wear white veils before they are married.", "answer": "<b> bride</b>s (accept<b> wife</b>, even after \u201cJewish\u201d is read; accept The Jewish<b> Bride</b> or Het Joodse <b>bruidje</b>; prompt on women, girls, etc.)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Knowledge of this text was greatly advanced with the discovery of the Mawangdui silk manuscripts and the Guodian slips. This text, which compares \u201cruling a large state\u201d to (+)\u201cboiling a delicate fish,\u201d was allegedly produced when a guard asked its author to share his wisdom before leaving the country on a water buffalo. It notes that a wise leader practices\u201cinaction, and the people look after themselves\u201d and begins with the assertion that the (*)</b> Way is nameless. For ten points, name this text allegedly penned by Lao Tzu, the principal text of Daoism.", "answer": "<b> Tao Te Ching</b> (or<b> Daodejing</b>; accept<b> Laozi</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>A geologic formation within this state includes the Ozona Arch and Val Verde Basin, and</b> <b>its Yates Oil Field is located west of the Edwards Plateau in this state\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Trans-Pecos.</b> <b>In the 1920s, the Cowden Field turned this state\u2019s cities of Odessa and Midland in the oil-producing Permian Basin into boom towns. The nation\u2019s largest refinery is found at (*) </b>Port Arthur here, and a salt dome in this state near Beaumont was the site of the Spindletop gusher in 1901. For ten points, many oil companies such as ConocoPhilips are headquartered in what state\u2019s largest city of Houston?", "answer": "<b> Texas</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "Integers could be factored</b> <b>in polynomial time on these devices by using (*)</b> Shor\u2019s algorithm, which would render RSA encryption useless. For ten points, name these devices that could improve upon the binary nature of computers by using qubits.", "answer": "<b> quantum computers</b> (prompt on computers) Page 9", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Computer Science"}, {"question": "<b>This justice joked that the Supreme Court had the power to determine what golf is in his dissent in</b><em><b> PGA Tour v. Martin</b></em><b>. This man called a ruling against antisodomy laws a product of \u201claw profession culture,\u201d and he called the legalization of gay marriage a (+)\u201cnaked claim to super-legislative power.\u201d This justice wrote that the individual right to carry arms was guaranteed in the majority opinion in</b><em><b> DC v. Heller</b></em><b>, and he echoed Stephen Breyer in calling an Obamacare ruling \u201cpure (*)</b> applesauce.\u201d For ten points, name this originalist justice whose 2016 death caused a lengthy vacancy on the Supreme Court.", "answer": "Antonin<b> Scalia</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This event was replicated in North Vietnam when two namesake journals were founded during the Nhan Van Giai Pham affair. This event was announced in the speech \u201cOn the</b> <b>Correct Handling of the Contradictions Among People.\u201d It led to the (+)</b> <b>Anti-Rightist</b> <b>Movement after the establishment of a \u201cDemocratic Wall\u201d and the outpouring of thousands of hostile letters prompted (*)</b> Mao Zedong to prosecute its participants. For ten points, name this Chinese Communist campaign in which citizens were encouraged to criticize their government.", "answer": "<b> Hundred Flowers</b> Movement (or Campaign, etc.; accept<b> Baihua</b> yundong)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man wrote in support of progressive politics in his</b><em><b> Commoner</b></em><b> magazine, and he noted that Christian values laid a foundation for group morality in his \u201cPrince of Peace\u201d</b> <b>speech, which he recited repeatedly on the (+)</b> <b>Chautauqua circuit. Years before the</b> <em><b>Lusitania</b></em><b> disaster prompted this man to resign as Woodrow Wilson\u2019s secretary of state, this man supported (*) </b> bimetallism, proclaiming that \u201cyou shall not crucify mankind\u201d in an 1896 convention speech. For ten points, name this Democratic presidential candidate who gave the \u201cCross of Gold\u201d speech.", "answer": "William Jennings<b> Bryan</b> Page 10", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}